"Is Six Hours of Sleep Enough?"
Conventional wisdom has it
that over the last 50 years
sleep duration has declined
in parallel with the increasing
prevalence of obesity,
suggesting that an epidemic
of sleep loss is associated with
the epidemic of weight gain.
Now, we have triple digit streaming
TV channels, smartphones,
and tablets to keep us entertained
well into the night.
"The hurry and excitement
of modern life is quite correctly
held to be responsible
for much of the insomnia,"
concluded one medical
journal editorial.
But that was an editorial
published in 1894.
Are we really sleeping
that much less?
Since 1905, sleep duration
in children and adolescents
has declined by a little
over an hour a night.
However, child labor wasn't
outlawed until 1938 though,
and so part of the explanation
may be due to the exhaustion
of sweating it out in the mines,
farms, and factories
in the early part of the last century.
Since 1970, youth sleep duration
has only declined about
15 minutes per night,
and it's not clear if sleep duration
in adults has changed much at all.
Based on 168 studies of objective
measurements of sleep duration,
instead of just self-report,
sleep duration in adults --
objective total sleep time --
has't changed much since 1960.
Since 2003, average sleep
duration in the United States
may have even gone up.
Now, of course, just because
we don't have evidence
that there's been a growing
epidemic of sleep deprivation
that doesn't necessarily mean
we're getting enough sleep.
Maybe we weren't getting enough
sleep 50 years ago either,
or since Edison's lightbulbs,
or since candles were
invented 5,000 years ago.
How might we determine
the optimal sleep duration?
One way would be to study
millions of people and see
how many hours a night is
associated with the longest lifespan.
Sleep is a great mystery.
A trait shared across animal species,
sleep must be of vital importance
to survive natural selection pressures
to eliminate such a vulnerable state.
Indeed, cringe-worthy
experiments have shown that
keeping animals awake long enough
is fatal within 11 to 32 days.
One of the functions of sleep that
has been elucidated in recent years
is the clearance of toxic
waste substances
that build up during the day
through a newly discovered
drainage system in the brain.
This could help explain why
those who routinely get
less than seven hours of sleep
at night may be at increased risk
of developing cognitive
disorders such as dementia.
Even a single all-nighter can
cause a significant increase
in beta amyloid accumulation
in critical brain areas,
a gummy substance implicated in the
development of Alzheimer's disease.
The lowest risk for developing
cognitive impairment was found
for those getting seven to
eight hours of sleep a night,
which is the same optimal range
found for diabetes risk,
based on 36 studies following
more than a million people.
The increased risk associated
with getting only six hours a night
compared to seven or eight
is comparable
to the increase in diabetes risk
linked to physical inactivity.
For death from all causes combined,
there's been more than 50 studies
following hundreds of thousands
of people for up to 34 years.
Sleeping too short and too long
are both associated
with cutting one's life short,
with the apparent sweet spot
at seven hours a night.
Seven hours may seem short,
but that may actually be
what's natural for our species.
Scientists studied three isolated
pre-industrial societies
across two continents and
found a surprising uniformity.
Despite no electric lighting
or gadgets,
they stayed up until
about three hours
after sunset and then
typically rose before dawn,
accumulating about a solid
six and a half hours of sleep
out of about seven and
a half hours in "bed."
A mechanism by which excess sleep
might be harmful remains elusive,
and so the association between
increased risk of death and disease
and sleeping nine or more hours
a night has been largely dismissed
as implausible.
Maybe its reverse causation,
sickness leading to more time
in bed instead of vice-versa,
or confounding factors
such as employment status.
After all, who gets to sleep in?
Those without a job to get to.
However, there is experimental
evidence showing negative
health effects from insufficient sleep.
So in terms of sleeping
in the sweet spot, aim for at least
seven hours of regular sleep a day.